"Three Reasons Fruits and Vegetables
May Reduce Osteoporosis Risk"
Even just
a single extra serving
of fruits
and vegetables per day
is associated
with lower bone fracture risk.
Why?
Well, osteoporotic fracture risk
is associated
with higher levels
of inflammation
in your blood,
for example,
C-reactive protein,
and specifically,
a more pro-inflammatory diet.
Those eating higher on
the dietary inflammatory index
have about a 30 percent
greater risk
of osteoporosis
and fracture
than those eating
more anti-inflammatory diets,
and a higher intake
of fruits and vegetables
decreases inflammation.
So, that's one possible reason.
Free radicals
may also play a role
in eating away at your bone,
suggesting that pro-oxidant
stress may contribute
to osteoporosis.
Both the total antioxidant power
and capacity of people's
bloodstreams and diets
are significantly lower
in those with osteoporosis,
and how do we squash
free radicals
and improve antioxidant status?
With fruits and vegetables.
For example, consumption
of vitamin C-rich foods
is associated with lower risk
of hip fracture, osteoporosis,
and bone loss.
Every additional increase of
50mg of dietary vitamin C a day,
which is about
the equivalent of one orange,
may lower the risk of hip
fracture by 5 percent.
The third way fruits and
vegetables may help our bones
is through acid-base balance.
As we grow older,
there's a slight drop
in the pH of our blood,
as our blood becomes
more acidic with age.
This is thought to be due to the
waning ability of our kidneys
to excrete excess acid.
In vitro studies suggest a drop
in pH may lead to activation
of the cells
that break down bone
and an inhibition of cells
that build bone back up.
So, how about eating
alkaline-forming foods?
The most acid-forming foods
are meat and cheese,
especially fish,
and the most alkaline,
or base-forming, foods
are fruits and vegetables.
This may help explain why
if you experimentally
remove fruits and vegetables
from people's diets,
a marker of bone formation
significantly drops,
and a marker of bone loss
shoots up,
and vice-versa when you
add fruits and vegetables
back into their daily diets.
The greater the estimated ratio
between acid-forming foods
and alkaline-forming foods,
the greater the risk
of hip fracture,
supporting the rationale
to eat less acidic diets,
but this was based
on observational data.
To prove cause-and-effect,
two-year, double-blind,
randomized controlled trials
were performed in which
the three added servings
of fruits and vegetables,
or the equivalent
of six extra servings,
failed to have an effect.
But randomize people
to the equivalent
of nine daily servings
of fruits' and vegetables' worth
of an alkaline-forming compound
and you do see
a significant increase
in bone volume and density
in the spine, hip,
and throughout the whole body.
Are there any
fruits and vegetables
that are particularly good?
That's the question
I'll address next.